<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kalecki | ShadowSwiss Economics</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tag/kalecki/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tag/kalecki/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Kalecki</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_huc57125e40b50a7b55b541ff0c8e05236_68374_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Kalecki</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tag/kalecki/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reevaluating Switzerland&#39;s Unemployment Success Story</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In macroeconomic theory, unemployment is a key factor. Despite the waning economic significance attributed to it with the rise of monetarism, which shifted focus from combating unemployment to combating inflation, economists still closely scrutinize its value. For instance, Blanchard&amp;rsquo;s recent macroeconomic manual positions unemployment as one of the key indicators of economic performance, trailing closely behind growth&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This economic variable holds heightened importance within the Swiss context. As elucidated in two recent articles&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Switzerland appears to be excelling, nearing full employment. This exceptional scenario, a rarity on the global stage, is sometimes perceived as nearly miraculous. Certain authors in academic literature even go as far as labeling it a « miracle »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, solidifying Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s low unemployment rate as an established and undisputed fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to this prevailing narrative, the subsequent analysis critically examines the success of Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s unemployment rate. While Switzerland indeed possesses unique characteristics compared to international counterparts, the following discussion delves into the concept of unemployment and the manner in which statistics rationalize it. Thus, it sidesteps the analysis of the causes and consequences of unemployment trends and instead focuses on the question of what unemployment signifies and how it is measured in the Swiss context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unemployment-a-numeric-entity-or-a-social-and-historical-construct&#34;&gt;Unemployment: A numeric entity or a social and historical construct?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, it proves beneficial to establish a definition and comprehension of unemployment. In economics, unemployment is often quantified through the unemployment rate, defined as « the number of people who do not have a job but are looking for one »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Assuming the labor force ($L$) comprises employment ($N$) and unemployment ($U$) (1), the unemployment rate ($u$) is calculated as the ratio of the number of unemployed individuals (2)&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
L = N + U \quad \text{(1)}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
u = \frac{U}{L} \quad \text{(2)}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this definition may appear straightforward, Blanchard cautions that « the unemployment rate is less obvious than it might seem »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a slightly different perspective, unemployment is sometimes conceptualized as « a historical and social construct specific to our Western societies&amp;hellip; the result of a process that took place mainly at the end of the nineteenth century, at the beginning of the twentieth century and in the thirties »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Within this political-economic framework, unemployment is neither self-evident nor static. Its measurement and definition fluctuate based on the evolution of the productive economic landscape, and the prevailing economic policies of a given era&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, unemployment is, in itself, a legal standard that varies significantly from one country to another and evolves over time in response to political decisions&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Unlike the other, this perspective highlights, therefore, the challenge that lies behind its measurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unemployment-rates-and-measurement-issues&#34;&gt;Unemployment rates and measurement issues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the aforementioned complexities and the intricate nature of paid employment (including internships, outsourcing, mandates) and forms of inactivity not encompassed in traditional unemployment metrics (such as underemployment, school dropout rates, reliance on social assistance, etc.), few economists subscribe to the existence of a singular true unemployment figure. Despite the adoption of a common unemployment definition by all countries since 1982 through the International Labour Organization (ILO), according to Sheldon, an economics professor at Basel University, « there&amp;rsquo;s no such thing as a &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; unemployment number »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The ILO definition allows indeed for considerable maneuvering, rendering international comparisons challenging&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and proving unsuitable for non-Western contexts&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, alternative indicators have emerged. While the number of measures varies by country, Switzerland primarily employs three main metrics&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; below illustrates the disparity between these metrics, showcasing the variation in unemployment rates between the second quarter of 2022 and the fourth quarter of 2023. Throughout this period, the ILO unemployment rate consistently exceeds that reported by the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO). Notably, the jobless rate, which includes underemployment, stands significantly higher than both. The jobless rate is on average 102% higher than the indicator calculated according ILO&amp;rsquo;s definition and 338% higher than that of the SECO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plota_hubeae451a93d26855c2427b6dc43031b4_28973_5f9ed5a9bf8951e258125d72fd7edf94.webp 400w,
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plota_hubeae451a93d26855c2427b6dc43031b4_28973_89eba32a35fc9e2fc43c61657583b4c3.webp 760w,
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plota_hubeae451a93d26855c2427b6dc43031b4_28973_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plota_hubeae451a93d26855c2427b6dc43031b4_28973_5f9ed5a9bf8951e258125d72fd7edf94.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;698&#34;
               height=&#34;498&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discrepancies stem chiefly from variations in definitions and measurement methodologies employed by these indicators. SECO&amp;rsquo;s metric, a widely recognized measure used for economic policymaking, relies on the number of individuals registered as unemployed with employment offices at month-end. Despite its monthly publication advantage, this metric suffers from a notable weakness: individuals without a compelling reason to register, such as those who have exhausted their unemployment benefits, likely abstain from visiting employment offices, thereby remaining uncounted. This registration-based measurement, prevalent internationally, remains susceptible to legal modifications. As noted by Blanchard, « in countries with less generous benefit systems, fewer unemployed individuals are likely to register, resulting in lower measured unemployment rates »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address these issues and enhance cross-country comparability, metrics aligned with the ILO definition have been developed by the Federal Statistical Office of Switzerland (FSO). Unlike SECO&amp;rsquo;s metric, which relies on registered individuals, this approach utilizes survey data, capturing the entirety of the resident population, published quarterly. While this methodology captures unregistered unemployment, its statistical accuracy may be compromised due to its survey nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the jobless rate, published by the FSO, transcends mere non-employment by incorporating individuals seeking increased work percentage, i.e. underemployment. This measure, known as the underemployment rate, is added to the ILO unemployment rate to derive the jobless rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-unsuccessful-unemployment-rate&#34;&gt;An unsuccessful unemployment rate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the rate calculated by SECO appears to be particularly performant, despite the methodological limitations already mentioned, a comparison of the jobless rate at European level paints an entirely different picture. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; shows an approximation of the quarterly jobless rate between 2015 and 2023 for the European Union, Germany, France, Austria and Switzerland. This is an approximation, as the rate is generally calculated as a percentage of the labor force. For reasons of comparability and data availability, it has only been possible to extract data as a percentage of the total population, which explains the differences between the figures for Switzerland in Figures 1 and 2. These data come from Eurostat and have been calculated according to the following equation (3):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ J_t = I_t + U_{nt} \quad \text{(3)} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;black&#34;&gt;$J_t$&lt;/font&gt;: The jobless rate, expressed as a % of the total population, covering ages 15 to 74, for a quarter $t$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;black&#34;&gt;$I_t$&lt;/font&gt;: Harmonized unemployment rate according to the ILO definition, expressed as a % of the total population, seasonally adjusted, covering ages 15 to 74, for a quarter$t$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;black&#34;&gt;$U_{nt}$&lt;/font&gt;: Underemployment rate expressed as a % of the total population, seasonally adjusted, covering ages 15 to 74, for a quarter $t$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the limits to the comparability of data due to the weaknesses of harmonization, &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; provides a major lesson: the approximate unemployment rate, captured by the jobless rate, will underperform Austria and Germany from 2015 to 2023. With the exception of the first two quarters of 2015, the Swiss unemployment rate is even higher than for the European Union as a whole. Switzerland only performs better than France, but this is not even true for the whole period, since France performs better in the last quarter of 2018, the third quarter of 2019, and all quarters of 2020 and 2021. As a result, Switzerland does not appear to be performing any better than the rest of Europe. In fact, compared with the European Union, Austria and Germany, it appears to be underperforming over the 2015-2023 period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plotb_hu5c9e0641aea5b3781b7364ade087a765_61555_3b3fddaf197f429706beb7a1300e2f0c.webp 400w,
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plotb_hu5c9e0641aea5b3781b7364ade087a765_61555_24fbeb25b83a560ee488b9d450af72c0.webp 760w,
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plotb_hu5c9e0641aea5b3781b7364ade087a765_61555_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plotb_hu5c9e0641aea5b3781b7364ade087a765_61555_3b3fddaf197f429706beb7a1300e2f0c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;698&#34;
               height=&#34;498&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-politics-behind-performance-or-why-a-very-low-unemployment-is-not-very-likely&#34;&gt;The politics behind performance or why a very &amp;lsquo;&amp;rsquo;low&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; unemployment is not very likely&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having demonstrated that the unemployment rate may not necessarily denote success depending on the indicator employed, it&amp;rsquo;s pertinent to assert that any extreme moderate figure appears not very plausible. In a simplified model structured around the capital-labor conflict, achieving full employment becomes inherently challenging. According to a Kaleckian model, unemployment serves as a disciplinary tool for workers, introducing job insecurity as a means of exerting control and tilting the balance of power&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Without unemployment, workers would possess greater leverage to demand wage increases and switch jobs at their discretion. In an economy prioritizing the interests of capital, full employment emerges as counterproductive. This begs the question: does Switzerland operate as an economy organized around labor ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is unequivocally no. As recent wage statistics show, real wages in Switzerland have fallen in recent years&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t to suggest that certain sectors may not exhibit favorable power dynamics for workers, but rather that, on average, it appears highly improbable that all workers benefit from favorable power relations in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the examination of Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s unemployment rate reveals a nuanced narrative that challenges the prevailing perception of its economic success. While Switzerland indeed boasts low unemployment rates, our analysis uncovers inherent complexities and disparities in both its measurement and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this article emphasizes the necessity of understanding how unemployment is defined and measured to comprehend its causes, consequences, and potential solutions fully. It does not aim to discredit the validity of existing metrics but rather to shed light on the limitations of their interpretation. Particularly noteworthy is the recognition that unemployment figures represent averages, often obscuring significant variations when analyzed across different social and economic categories&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, delving into Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s unemployment rate serves as a crucial reminder of the intricate nature of economic indicators and the importance of contextualizing their analysis within broader socio-political frameworks. By moving beyond surface-level statistics, we attain deeper insights into the complexities of economic performance and the underlying forces that shape our economic system and influence our perceptions of it. Noteworthy studies have, for example, highlighted correlations between fluctuations in the unemployment rate and shifts in government popularity&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and partisan voting patterns&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Hence, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to view unemployment not just as a straightforward statistic, but as a dynamic measure with political implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blanchard, O (2020). Macroeconomics, Global edition. 8th edition, Pearson.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rts.ch/info/economie/14453073-avec-un-taux-de-chomage-de-2-on-peut-parler-de-plein-emploi-en-suisse.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.rts.ch/info/economie/14453073-avec-un-taux-de-chomage-de-2-on-peut-parler-de-plein-emploi-en-suisse.html&lt;/a&gt; ; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rts.ch/info/economie/2024/article/plein-emploi-la-detresse-de-ceux-qui-ne-trouvent-pas-28475514.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.rts.ch/info/economie/2024/article/plein-emploi-la-detresse-de-ceux-qui-ne-trouvent-pas-28475514.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merrien, F. X., &amp;amp; Becker, U. (2005). The Swiss miracle: Low growth and high employment. Employment &amp;lsquo;Miracles&amp;rsquo;: A critical comparison of the Dutch, Scandinavian, Swiss, Australian and Irish cases versus Germany and the US, 113-132; Siegenthaler, M., Graff, M., &amp;amp; Mannino, M. (2014). The Swiss&amp;rsquo; Job Miracle&amp;rsquo;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blanchard (2020), p.45.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem, p.46.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gautié, J. (2002). De l&amp;rsquo;invention du chômage à sa déconstruction. Genèses, (2), 60-76, p.60.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem; Gautié, J. (2023). The rise and demise of unemployment. In Handbook of Labour Market Policy in Advanced Democracies (pp. 14-26). Edward Elgar Publishing.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/fr/2020/09/sheldon-10-2020fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/fr/2020/09/sheldon-10-2020fr/&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gautié, J. (2023).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benanav, A. (2019). The origins of informality: the ILO at the limit of the concept of unemployment. Journal of Global History, 14(1), 107-125.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The employment rate is also increasingly used as an alternative measure to the unemployment rate. In this article, however, we consider that it is not really an unemployment rate as its name suggests.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blanchard (2020), p. 46.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kalecki, M. (1943). Political aspects of full employment.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/fr/home/statistiques/travail-remuneration/salaires-revenus-cout-travail/indice-salaires.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/fr/home/statistiques/travail-remuneration/salaires-revenus-cout-travail/indice-salaires.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unemployment rate for all three metrics is consistently higher for women and foreigners, and in some cases for young people.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen, J. E., &amp;amp; King, J. D. (2004). Relative unemployment and gubernatorial popularity. The Journal of Politics, 66(4), 1267-1282; Ansolabehere, S., Meredith, M., &amp;amp; Snowberg, E. (2014). Mecro‐economic voting: Local information and micro‐perceptions of the macro‐economy. Economics &amp;amp; Politics, 26(3), 380-410.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wright, J. R. (2012). Unemployment and the democratic electoral advantage. American Political Science Review, 106(4), 685-702; Brännlund, A. (2021). Labor market conditions and partisan voting: How unemployment hurts the left. Political Behavior, 43(1), 363-396.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Profit-Investment nexus in Switzerland</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/financialization/untitledrmd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/financialization/untitledrmd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Swiss economy has long been regarded as impervious to economic turmoil, lauded for its prosperity, robust performance, and macroeconomic stability&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Many view it as a resilient economic structure capable of withstanding any challenge. Amid such perceptions, few dare to suggest that it is in a state of disrepair, relegating critical analysis to the realm of the anecdotal and the improbable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to this simplistic viewpoint, this article aims to demonstrate the susceptibility of the Swiss economy to the structural economic changes that have emerged in recent decades. Specifically, it focuses on the impact of financialization on the profit and investment dynamics of non-financial corporations. In this context, financialization refers to the increasing influence of shareholders in corporate governance and its complex financial implications&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. One particular contradiction highlighted in the literature is the paradox of declining investment alongside increasing profits, commonly known as the &lt;em&gt;investment-profit puzzle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this puzzle has been observed in several countries&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, it has received minimal attention in Switzerland. Therefore, this article aims to examine the relationship between investment and profit within the Swiss context, beginning with a concise overview of the relevant literature. It subsequently delves into illustrating the profit-investment interconnection in Switzerland, ultimately offering insights into the sustainability of these dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;corporate-financialization-and-his-impact-on-the-profit-investment-nexus&#34;&gt;Corporate financialization and his impact on the profit-investment nexus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While financialization may refer to a new accumulation regime or the heightened influence of finance in everyday life&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, numerous studies have focused on its implications at the corporate level. In this corporate dimension, financialization specifically alludes to the emergence of &lt;em&gt;shareholder value orientation&lt;/em&gt; (SVO) in the 1980s in the United States, which amplified the power of shareholders in corporate governance&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The literature emphasizes the financial consequences of this ascendant shareholder influence, particularly the shift from &lt;em&gt;retain and reinvest&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;downsize and distribute&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In addition to the impact on headcount, these studies underscore the altered utilization of profits, with less being channeled into investments and more being distributed among shareholders&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While corporate financialization predominantly features at the microeconomic level, it has been employed in several studies to elucidate macroeconomic dynamics. Particularly, it has been invoked to explain the disparity between profits and investment at the macroeconomic level. Drawing from Kalecki&amp;rsquo;s profit equation&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, macroeconomic profits heavily rely on macroeconomic investment. Understanding this dependency necessitates a brief examination of this equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a simplified framework where capitalists and workers are the primary agents, and with negligible government spending and consumption equating to wages, Kalecki&amp;rsquo;s equation can be expressed as follows&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Factoring in the absence of management and raw material purchases, the macroeconomic profits (Π) of corporations are the difference between their sales (SA) and total costs (TC). In this simplified equation (1), profit equals the disparity between prices (p) multiplied by quantities (Q) and wages paid (W):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Π = 𝑆𝐴 − 𝑇𝐶 = 𝑝𝑄 − 𝑊 (1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As prices multiplied by quantities correspond to aggregate demand, and with no public spending, profits can be expressed as the sum of consumption (C) and investment (I) - wages paid, as outlined in equation (2):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Π = 𝑝𝑄 − 𝑊 = (𝐶 + 𝐼) − 𝑊 (2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while consumption equals wages (C=W) in a model where workers spend what they earn, profits are equivalent to investment, as indicated in equation (3). Introducing a causal relationship where investment drives profits renders Kalecki&amp;rsquo;s argument even more compelling: profits without investment are simply unattainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Π = 𝐼 (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the relevance of this demonstration, Kalecki&amp;rsquo;s profit equation faces significant challenges in the era of financialization. Numerous studies highlight a profound paradox: despite the decline in investments under SVO pressure, profits continue to surge&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. To elucidate this paradox of profits without investment, some studies have been compelled to consider other explanatory variables, such as globalization and monopolization&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;profits-without-investment-or-no-profits-without-investment-&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profits without investment&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;No profits without investment&lt;/em&gt; ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before examining the profit-investment nexus within the Swiss context, it is crucial to briefly outline our methodology. Non-financial corporations&amp;rsquo; profits will be evaluated in terms of gross operating surplus, a metric that not only indicates profitability in relation to gross value added at the macroeconomic level&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but also enables an examination of how profits are allocated. Specifically, it allows for an assessment of the proportion of profits distributed to shareholders and creditors versus those reinvested in productive capital&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Investment will be assessed in terms of gross capital formation, representing investment in productive capital&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Moreover, financialization will be evaluated based on shareholder payments relative to investment, capturing the essence of SVO and its downsize and distribute principle at the macroeconomic level&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. All data is drawn from the national accounts published by the Federal Statistical Office of Switzerland (FSO). However, the measurements of profitability, profit allocation, and financialization are the result of personal calculations for which the author of this article bears sole responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; below depicts the profit-investment nexus in Switzerland amid the context of financialization. It illustrates the consistent increase in downsize and distribute by Swiss non-financial corporations compared to the decline in their profits between 1995 and 2022. With the exception of the late 1990s, dividends paid to shareholders have outpaced productive investment, while profit share witnessed a significant decline, notably between 2005 and 2020. Contrary to prevalant notions concerning its economy, Switzerland has undergone a dramatic transformation. Swiss non-financial corporations have distributed more than they have invested, leading to a decrease in their capacity to generate profits. By allocating a greater share of their profits to shareholders at the expense of investment, companies are endangering their long-term growth, aligning with Kalecki&amp;rsquo;s profit framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/financialization/UntitledRMD_files/Fig10.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 1&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-contradiction-of-profits&#34;&gt;The contradiction of profits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bolster our argument, &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; illustrates the trend of profits for Swiss non-financial corporations between 1995 and 2022. It demonstrates that while the share of profits going to creditors has declined and the share going to investors has remained relatively stable, the share going to shareholders has experienced a sharp rise. Since the advent of &lt;em&gt;financialization Mark II&lt;/em&gt; in the year 2000&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, profits intended for shareholders have, on average, grown 2.84 times faster than those allocated for investment. This illustration serves as a secondary validation. With the ascent of SVO, the balance sheets of Swiss non-financial corporations have become increasingly precarious. Since 2014, more than 100% of profits have been expended, a phenomenon explicable by two dynamics: either corporate savings leading to the expenditure of more profits than exist, or increased corporate borrowing. In either scenario, this SVO pressure is not sustainable in the medium term. In the current environment of high inflation and increased interest rates, Swiss non-financial corporations are confronted with the decision of whether to curtail shareholder payouts or productive investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/financialization/UntitledRMD_files/Fig2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 2&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;concluding-remarks&#34;&gt;Concluding remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it is essential to acknowledge that this article has not captured all the factors contributing to the decline in investment and profits. For instance, globalization may explain a potential shift of productive investments to third countries, while the monopolization of US technological firms could adversely impact the profit generation of Swiss non-financial corporations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these limitations, this article delivers a critical lesson: contrary to the prevailing emphasis on Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s economic success and stability, it highlights a significant failure within the context of financialization. The profits of non-financial corporations have diminished as distribution to shareholders is prioritized over investment. Moreover, since 2014, this transformation has posed a notable challenge, leading to a contraction of corporate balance sheets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond its importance in understanding the contemporary Swiss economy, this article contributes more broadly to the literature concerning the &lt;em&gt;investment-profit puzzle&lt;/em&gt;. Indeed, it shows that unlike many national contexts, Switzerland does not have a puzzle. Continuing Kalecki&amp;rsquo;s profit equation, the declining macroeconomic investment leads to declining macroeconomic profits. Switzerland is therefore not faced with &lt;em&gt;profits without investment&lt;/em&gt;, but rather with &lt;em&gt;no profits without investment&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a review see Mach, A., &amp;amp; Trampusch, C. (2011). The Swiss political economy in comparative perspective. Switzerland in Europe. Continuity and change in the Swiss political economy, 11-26.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lazonick, W., &amp;amp; O&amp;rsquo;sullivan, M. (2000). Maximizing shareholder value: a new ideology for corporate governance. Economy and society, 29(1), 13-35.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stockhammer, E. (2005). Shareholder value orientation and the investment-profit puzzle. Journal of Post Keynesian Economics, 28(2), 193-215; Cordonnier, L. (2006). Le profit sans l&amp;rsquo;accumulation: la recette du capitalisme gouverné par la finance. Innovations, (1), 79-108; Durand, C., &amp;amp; Gueuder, M. (2018). The profit&amp;ndash;investment nexus in an era of financialisation, globalisation and monopolisation: A profit-centred perspective. Review of political economy, 30(2), 126-153; Rabinovich, J. (2021). Financialisation and the &amp;lsquo;supply-side&amp;rsquo;face of the investment-profit puzzle. Journal of Post Keynesian Economics, 44(3), 434-462.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly the OECD countries. See for example, Stockhammer, E. (2005) and Durand, C., &amp;amp; Gueuder, M. (2018).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a broad definition, see Van der Zwan, N. (2014). Making sense of financialization. Socio-economic review, 12(1), 99-129.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lazonick-O&amp;rsquo;Sullivan (2000).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a broad review see Auvray, T., Dallery, T., &amp;amp; Rigot, S. (2016). L&amp;rsquo;entreprise liquidée: la finance contre l&amp;rsquo;investissement.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kalecki, M. (1969). Theory of Economic Dynamics . New York: Augustus M. Kelley. (The original edition was published in 1952.)&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simplified presentation of Kalecki&amp;rsquo;s equation is mainly inspired by Auvray and al (2016).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stockhammer, E. (2005); Cordonnier, L. (2006); Durand, C., &amp;amp; Gueuder, M. (2018); Rabinovich, J. (2021).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Durand, C., &amp;amp; Gueuder, M. (2018); Auvray, T., Durand, C., Rabinovich, J., &amp;amp; Rikap, C. (2021). Corporate financialization&amp;rsquo;s conservation and transformation: from Mark I to Mark II. Review of Evolutionary Political Economy, 2, 431-457.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example, see Stockhammer, E. (2005).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example see Auvray and a.l (2021).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example, see Stockhammer, E. (2005); Cordonnier, L. (2006); Durand, C., &amp;amp; Gueuder, M. (2018); Rabinovich, J. (2021); Auvray and al (2021&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an example, see Botte, F., Cordonnier, L., Dallery, T., Duwicquet, V., Melmiès, J., &amp;amp; Van De Velde, F. (2017). Le coût du capital: entre pertes et détournement de richesses (Research dissertation, Université Lille 1-Sciences et Technologies; Université du littoral côte d&amp;rsquo;Opale; Clersé).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auvray and al (2021).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
