<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Political Economy | ShadowSwiss Economics</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tag/political-economy/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tag/political-economy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Political Economy</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_huc57125e40b50a7b55b541ff0c8e05236_68374_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Political Economy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tag/political-economy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who pollutes in Switzerland, consumers or producers?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024-08-13-who-pollutes-in-switzerland-consumers-or-producers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024-08-13-who-pollutes-in-switzerland-consumers-or-producers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the Nobel Prize-winning economist Jean Tirole, « the economy is everywhere, there&amp;rsquo;s no escaping it »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This assertion holds particular relevance in discussions about climate change. Indeed, understanding the causes and solutions to climate change necessitates to consider the economic dimension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the prevalent solution to tackle climate change is to change individual consumption patterns. In this perspective, changing consumption on an individual and voluntary basis is touted as sufficient to save the climate. This doctrine, which seems straightforward and widely accepted, aligns closely however with the controversial neoclassical theory of consumption&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and deliberately sidesteps what most constrains individual behavior: the capitalist mode of production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we will scrutinize how the dominant doctrine associated with &lt;em&gt;green liberalism&lt;/em&gt; is contradicted by empirical data from Switzerland. Additionally, we will demonstrate how contemporary ecological Marxist thought offers a framework to reintegrate climate change into tangible realities in Switzerland. In doing so, we aim to expose the limitations of the dominant doctrine from historical, political, and economic perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;green-liberalism-the-ideology-of-consumer-led-climate-solutions&#34;&gt;Green liberalism: the ideology of consumer-led climate solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, it is essential to unpack the core of the dominant doctrine. According to Steinberg, « the idea that market forces combined with individuals all doing their part can save the planet »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; encapsulates the essence of &lt;em&gt;green liberalism&lt;/em&gt;. This doctrine stems directly from the 80s and 90s, which saw the emergence of a new neoliberal economic era based on the progressive abandonment of collective values and solidarity in favor of unbridled individualism&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. For Steinberg, Margaret Thatcher&amp;rsquo;s famous declaration, &lt;em&gt;there is no society&lt;/em&gt;, epitomizes this shift towards « an environmental philosophy built on market worship and individual initiative »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, to bolster his demonstration, Steinberg points to the beverage industry as a telling example of this phenomenon. By tracing the legislative struggles surrounding recycling in the U.S. beverage industry, he reveals, indeed, how the industry has adeptly avoided regulation by shifting the burden of responsibility onto consumers&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In this context, « recycling constitutes a profoundly individual response to the problem of waste. It works to the advantage of industry by pushing the costs of business onto the public to bear. It also shields industry from any restrictions on its methods of production »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the notion that individual and voluntary changes in consumption can sufficiently address climate change reflects the ideology of &lt;em&gt;green liberalism&lt;/em&gt;. This doctrine first gained prominence during the neoliberal era of the 1980s and 1990s and was actively promoted by manufacturers. In particular, this strategic promotion aimed the industry to safeguard their profits in a potentially more regulated market environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fallacy-of-green-liberalism-why-consumer-actions-alone-wont-save-the-planet&#34;&gt;The fallacy of green liberalism: why consumer actions alone won&amp;rsquo;t save the planet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we have demonstrated that this doctrine arises from specific economic and political conditions, we have yet to address the effectiveness of its proposals. Despite its alignment with the neoliberal era and active promotion by industry, this doctrine could, in theory, offer a solution to climate change. Let us consider contemporary Marxist ecological thought to highlight two significant limitations of this doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;green liberalism&lt;/em&gt; to be effective, it would require that individual consumption be the primary driver of climate change. This would mean that the choices you and I make in purchasing goods and services are the main factors contributing to environmental degradation. If this were not the case, altering our consumption patterns would only have a negligible effect on mitigating climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this perspective is notably limited, not only because our consumption choices are far from entirely free and rational&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but also because Malm&amp;rsquo;s research argues that climate change is not driven by individual consumption choices at all. Instead, it traces back to the historical adoption of coal by manufacturers during the Industrial Revolution&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malm&amp;rsquo;s work highlights, indeed, that the shift to coal was not an inevitable or rational choice; hydroelectric power was actually more efficient and less costly. However, coal was favored because it allowed industrialists to discipline their workers more effectively&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Coal-powered factories could be located in cities where police forces and anti-labor norms were prevalent, providing a controlled environment that hydroelectricity, often located in rural areas, could not offer&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, according to Malm, climate change is rooted not in the limited consumption choices of individuals but in the emergence of fossil fuel capitalism driven by the strategic interests of producers, specifically their desire to maintain control over labor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This critique leads us to a deeper understanding of capitalism and why &lt;em&gt;green liberalism&lt;/em&gt; is insufficient for transforming it. &lt;em&gt;Green liberalism&lt;/em&gt; posits that changing consumption habits can fundamentally alter the economic structure. However, from a Marxist perspective, this is a flawed assumption. Capitalism is not merely a system of consumption; it is a specific mode of production that inherently shapes consumption patterns. The production process dictates what and how goods are consumed, not the other way around. For example, a worker is unlikely to purchase a yacht, whereas a wealthy capitalist CEO is far more likely to do so. As Marxist thought suggests, « consumption without production would have no object »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, because it is one&amp;rsquo;s position within the production system, whether as a worker or a capitalist, that determines income and, consequently, consumption. Therefore, focusing solely on individual, voluntary, and  limited isolated consumption choices fails to address the systemic nature of capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;marxist-empirical-evidence-producers-are-the-primary-contributors-to-co2-emissions-in-switzerland&#34;&gt;Marxist empirical evidence: producers are the primary contributors to CO2 emissions in Switzerland&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having examined both &lt;em&gt;green liberalism&lt;/em&gt; and ecological Marxism, it is now essential to evaluate their claims against empirical data. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; below presents total greenhouse gas emissions in millions of tonnes of CO2 equivalent by economic sector from 1991 to 2021. This data, sourced from the Federal Statistical Office of Switzerland (FSO) and calculated as a percentage by us, reveals that production&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is responsible for over 60% of the pollution, while consumption&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; accounts for just over 30% over the same period. This starkly contradicts the &lt;em&gt;green liberalism&lt;/em&gt; doctrine, which tends to emphasize individual consumption as the main factor in climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/HTML/Figd.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, this analysis focuses solely on greenhouse gases within national boundaries and does not account for the pollution generated by Swiss companies operating abroad&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Given the high level of internationalization of Swiss firms, including emissions from their overseas operations would likely increase the responsibility of producers even further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it&amp;rsquo;s important to consider that household emissions include those from transportation, which should be viewed not merely as consumption but as capital goods necessary for work-related activities. For instance, using a car for commuting to work should be seen as a functional necessity rather than a discretionary consumer choice&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. However, if an individual uses a Ferrari for leisure driving, that represents consumer behavior. Thus, attributing transport-related CO2 emissions directly to households without accounting for their socio-economic context likely inflates the perceived impact of consumer behavior. We can largely assume that, therefore, unlike the underestimated share of producers, the share attributed to consumption is overestimated&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, this article highlights the significant shortcomings of &lt;em&gt;green liberalism&lt;/em&gt;, which posits individual consumption changes as the primary solution to climate change. By overlooking the critical role of production in shaping consumption patterns, this doctrine offers an illusory solution that is flawed both theoretically and empirically. The Swiss data clearly shows that producers are responsible for a much larger share of CO2 emissions than individual consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implications of this analysis extend far beyond Switzerland, serving as a cautionary tale for anyone genuinely committed to combating climate change. It exposes the power of ideology in framing recycling or reducing meat consumption as revolutionary acts, when in reality, these individual limited choices fall short of addressing the root causes of the environmental damages. This depoliticization of climate action, which reduces the struggle to the limited consumption choices of isolated individuals, is deeply problematic because it distracts from the need for systemic change. Real progress in the fight against climate change will only come from collective action that challenges the underlying structure of production and directly confronts the true source of the problem: capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lemonde.fr/economie/article/2018/03/29/jean-tirole-l-economie-est-partout-on-ne-peut-y-echapper_4536784_3234.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.lemonde.fr/economie/article/2018/03/29/jean-tirole-l-economie-est-partout-on-ne-peut-y-echapper_4536784_3234.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a broad critique, see Keen, S. (2001). Debunking economics: The naked emperor of the social sciences. Zed Books; Lee, F. S., &amp;amp; Keen, S. (2004). The incoherent emperor: a heterodox critique of neoclassical microeconomic theory. Review of Social Economy, 62(2), 169-199.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steinberg, T. (2010). Can capitalism save the planet? On the origins of green liberalism. Radical history review, 2010(107), 7-24, p.8.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem, p.13.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem, p.13.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the neoclassical theory of consumption, which assumes that consumers make free and rational choices, the reality is far more complex. Consumers are influenced by a range of factors, including cultural and social norms, their income levels, and corporate strategies designed to increase sales. These strategies encompass marketing, neuromarketing, product placement in stores, promotional activities, advertising, packaging, and the selection of available products. As a result, consumer choices are far from entirely free or rational. For a more comprehensive critique of consumer rationality, see Keen (2001).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malm, A. (2016). Fossil capital: The rise of steam power and the roots of global warming. Verso books.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marx, K. (1857). Introduction to a Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy. idem, Grundrisse, 81-114, online version : &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1859/critique-pol-economy/appx1.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1859/critique-pol-economy/appx1.htm&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to FSO, what we call production represents the economy, i.e the threemain sectors (primary, secondary, tertiary).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to FSO, what we call consumption represents households.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is mainly due to the domestic concept that characterizes the national accounts.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a review of this particular distinction, see Clouscard, M. (2013). Néo-fascisme et idéologie du désir. Editions Delga.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it is worth noting that this analysis only considers air pollution by economic sector. In the future, it would be interesting to have statistics that also delineate the share of responsibility in terms of water and soil pollution.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reevaluating Switzerland&#39;s Unemployment Success Story</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In macroeconomic theory, unemployment is a key factor. Despite the waning economic significance attributed to it with the rise of monetarism, which shifted focus from combating unemployment to combating inflation, economists still closely scrutinize its value. For instance, Blanchard&amp;rsquo;s recent macroeconomic manual positions unemployment as one of the key indicators of economic performance, trailing closely behind growth&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This economic variable holds heightened importance within the Swiss context. As elucidated in two recent articles&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Switzerland appears to be excelling, nearing full employment. This exceptional scenario, a rarity on the global stage, is sometimes perceived as nearly miraculous. Certain authors in academic literature even go as far as labeling it a « miracle »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, solidifying Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s low unemployment rate as an established and undisputed fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to this prevailing narrative, the subsequent analysis critically examines the success of Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s unemployment rate. While Switzerland indeed possesses unique characteristics compared to international counterparts, the following discussion delves into the concept of unemployment and the manner in which statistics rationalize it. Thus, it sidesteps the analysis of the causes and consequences of unemployment trends and instead focuses on the question of what unemployment signifies and how it is measured in the Swiss context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unemployment-a-numeric-entity-or-a-social-and-historical-construct&#34;&gt;Unemployment: A numeric entity or a social and historical construct?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, it proves beneficial to establish a definition and comprehension of unemployment. In economics, unemployment is often quantified through the unemployment rate, defined as « the number of people who do not have a job but are looking for one »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Assuming the labor force ($L$) comprises employment ($N$) and unemployment ($U$) (1), the unemployment rate ($u$) is calculated as the ratio of the number of unemployed individuals (2)&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
L = N + U \quad \text{(1)}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
u = \frac{U}{L} \quad \text{(2)}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this definition may appear straightforward, Blanchard cautions that « the unemployment rate is less obvious than it might seem »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a slightly different perspective, unemployment is sometimes conceptualized as « a historical and social construct specific to our Western societies&amp;hellip; the result of a process that took place mainly at the end of the nineteenth century, at the beginning of the twentieth century and in the thirties »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Within this political-economic framework, unemployment is neither self-evident nor static. Its measurement and definition fluctuate based on the evolution of the productive economic landscape, and the prevailing economic policies of a given era&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, unemployment is, in itself, a legal standard that varies significantly from one country to another and evolves over time in response to political decisions&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Unlike the other, this perspective highlights, therefore, the challenge that lies behind its measurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unemployment-rates-and-measurement-issues&#34;&gt;Unemployment rates and measurement issues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the aforementioned complexities and the intricate nature of paid employment (including internships, outsourcing, mandates) and forms of inactivity not encompassed in traditional unemployment metrics (such as underemployment, school dropout rates, reliance on social assistance, etc.), few economists subscribe to the existence of a singular true unemployment figure. Despite the adoption of a common unemployment definition by all countries since 1982 through the International Labour Organization (ILO), according to Sheldon, an economics professor at Basel University, « there&amp;rsquo;s no such thing as a &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; unemployment number »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The ILO definition allows indeed for considerable maneuvering, rendering international comparisons challenging&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and proving unsuitable for non-Western contexts&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, alternative indicators have emerged. While the number of measures varies by country, Switzerland primarily employs three main metrics&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; below illustrates the disparity between these metrics, showcasing the variation in unemployment rates between the second quarter of 2022 and the fourth quarter of 2023. Throughout this period, the ILO unemployment rate consistently exceeds that reported by the State Secretariat for Economic Affairs (SECO). Notably, the jobless rate, which includes underemployment, stands significantly higher than both. The jobless rate is on average 102% higher than the indicator calculated according ILO&amp;rsquo;s definition and 338% higher than that of the SECO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plota_hubeae451a93d26855c2427b6dc43031b4_28973_5f9ed5a9bf8951e258125d72fd7edf94.webp 400w,
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plota_hubeae451a93d26855c2427b6dc43031b4_28973_89eba32a35fc9e2fc43c61657583b4c3.webp 760w,
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plota_hubeae451a93d26855c2427b6dc43031b4_28973_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plota_hubeae451a93d26855c2427b6dc43031b4_28973_5f9ed5a9bf8951e258125d72fd7edf94.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;698&#34;
               height=&#34;498&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discrepancies stem chiefly from variations in definitions and measurement methodologies employed by these indicators. SECO&amp;rsquo;s metric, a widely recognized measure used for economic policymaking, relies on the number of individuals registered as unemployed with employment offices at month-end. Despite its monthly publication advantage, this metric suffers from a notable weakness: individuals without a compelling reason to register, such as those who have exhausted their unemployment benefits, likely abstain from visiting employment offices, thereby remaining uncounted. This registration-based measurement, prevalent internationally, remains susceptible to legal modifications. As noted by Blanchard, « in countries with less generous benefit systems, fewer unemployed individuals are likely to register, resulting in lower measured unemployment rates »&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address these issues and enhance cross-country comparability, metrics aligned with the ILO definition have been developed by the Federal Statistical Office of Switzerland (FSO). Unlike SECO&amp;rsquo;s metric, which relies on registered individuals, this approach utilizes survey data, capturing the entirety of the resident population, published quarterly. While this methodology captures unregistered unemployment, its statistical accuracy may be compromised due to its survey nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the jobless rate, published by the FSO, transcends mere non-employment by incorporating individuals seeking increased work percentage, i.e. underemployment. This measure, known as the underemployment rate, is added to the ILO unemployment rate to derive the jobless rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-unsuccessful-unemployment-rate&#34;&gt;An unsuccessful unemployment rate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the rate calculated by SECO appears to be particularly performant, despite the methodological limitations already mentioned, a comparison of the jobless rate at European level paints an entirely different picture. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; shows an approximation of the quarterly jobless rate between 2015 and 2023 for the European Union, Germany, France, Austria and Switzerland. This is an approximation, as the rate is generally calculated as a percentage of the labor force. For reasons of comparability and data availability, it has only been possible to extract data as a percentage of the total population, which explains the differences between the figures for Switzerland in Figures 1 and 2. These data come from Eurostat and have been calculated according to the following equation (3):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ J_t = I_t + U_{nt} \quad \text{(3)} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;black&#34;&gt;$J_t$&lt;/font&gt;: The jobless rate, expressed as a % of the total population, covering ages 15 to 74, for a quarter $t$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;black&#34;&gt;$I_t$&lt;/font&gt;: Harmonized unemployment rate according to the ILO definition, expressed as a % of the total population, seasonally adjusted, covering ages 15 to 74, for a quarter$t$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;font color=&#34;black&#34;&gt;$U_{nt}$&lt;/font&gt;: Underemployment rate expressed as a % of the total population, seasonally adjusted, covering ages 15 to 74, for a quarter $t$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the limits to the comparability of data due to the weaknesses of harmonization, &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; provides a major lesson: the approximate unemployment rate, captured by the jobless rate, will underperform Austria and Germany from 2015 to 2023. With the exception of the first two quarters of 2015, the Swiss unemployment rate is even higher than for the European Union as a whole. Switzerland only performs better than France, but this is not even true for the whole period, since France performs better in the last quarter of 2018, the third quarter of 2019, and all quarters of 2020 and 2021. As a result, Switzerland does not appear to be performing any better than the rest of Europe. In fact, compared with the European Union, Austria and Germany, it appears to be underperforming over the 2015-2023 period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plotb_hu5c9e0641aea5b3781b7364ade087a765_61555_3b3fddaf197f429706beb7a1300e2f0c.webp 400w,
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plotb_hu5c9e0641aea5b3781b7364ade087a765_61555_24fbeb25b83a560ee488b9d450af72c0.webp 760w,
               /post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plotb_hu5c9e0641aea5b3781b7364ade087a765_61555_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:4321/post/2024-05-03-reevaluating-switzerland-s-unemployment-success-story/images/Plotb_hu5c9e0641aea5b3781b7364ade087a765_61555_3b3fddaf197f429706beb7a1300e2f0c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;698&#34;
               height=&#34;498&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-politics-behind-performance-or-why-a-very-low-unemployment-is-not-very-likely&#34;&gt;The politics behind performance or why a very &amp;lsquo;&amp;rsquo;low&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; unemployment is not very likely&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having demonstrated that the unemployment rate may not necessarily denote success depending on the indicator employed, it&amp;rsquo;s pertinent to assert that any extreme moderate figure appears not very plausible. In a simplified model structured around the capital-labor conflict, achieving full employment becomes inherently challenging. According to a Kaleckian model, unemployment serves as a disciplinary tool for workers, introducing job insecurity as a means of exerting control and tilting the balance of power&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Without unemployment, workers would possess greater leverage to demand wage increases and switch jobs at their discretion. In an economy prioritizing the interests of capital, full employment emerges as counterproductive. This begs the question: does Switzerland operate as an economy organized around labor ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is unequivocally no. As recent wage statistics show, real wages in Switzerland have fallen in recent years&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t to suggest that certain sectors may not exhibit favorable power dynamics for workers, but rather that, on average, it appears highly improbable that all workers benefit from favorable power relations in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the examination of Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s unemployment rate reveals a nuanced narrative that challenges the prevailing perception of its economic success. While Switzerland indeed boasts low unemployment rates, our analysis uncovers inherent complexities and disparities in both its measurement and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this article emphasizes the necessity of understanding how unemployment is defined and measured to comprehend its causes, consequences, and potential solutions fully. It does not aim to discredit the validity of existing metrics but rather to shed light on the limitations of their interpretation. Particularly noteworthy is the recognition that unemployment figures represent averages, often obscuring significant variations when analyzed across different social and economic categories&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, delving into Switzerland&amp;rsquo;s unemployment rate serves as a crucial reminder of the intricate nature of economic indicators and the importance of contextualizing their analysis within broader socio-political frameworks. By moving beyond surface-level statistics, we attain deeper insights into the complexities of economic performance and the underlying forces that shape our economic system and influence our perceptions of it. Noteworthy studies have, for example, highlighted correlations between fluctuations in the unemployment rate and shifts in government popularity&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and partisan voting patterns&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Hence, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to view unemployment not just as a straightforward statistic, but as a dynamic measure with political implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blanchard, O (2020). Macroeconomics, Global edition. 8th edition, Pearson.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rts.ch/info/economie/14453073-avec-un-taux-de-chomage-de-2-on-peut-parler-de-plein-emploi-en-suisse.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.rts.ch/info/economie/14453073-avec-un-taux-de-chomage-de-2-on-peut-parler-de-plein-emploi-en-suisse.html&lt;/a&gt; ; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rts.ch/info/economie/2024/article/plein-emploi-la-detresse-de-ceux-qui-ne-trouvent-pas-28475514.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.rts.ch/info/economie/2024/article/plein-emploi-la-detresse-de-ceux-qui-ne-trouvent-pas-28475514.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merrien, F. X., &amp;amp; Becker, U. (2005). The Swiss miracle: Low growth and high employment. Employment &amp;lsquo;Miracles&amp;rsquo;: A critical comparison of the Dutch, Scandinavian, Swiss, Australian and Irish cases versus Germany and the US, 113-132; Siegenthaler, M., Graff, M., &amp;amp; Mannino, M. (2014). The Swiss&amp;rsquo; Job Miracle&amp;rsquo;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blanchard (2020), p.45.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem, p.46.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gautié, J. (2002). De l&amp;rsquo;invention du chômage à sa déconstruction. Genèses, (2), 60-76, p.60.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ibidem; Gautié, J. (2023). The rise and demise of unemployment. In Handbook of Labour Market Policy in Advanced Democracies (pp. 14-26). Edward Elgar Publishing.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/fr/2020/09/sheldon-10-2020fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://dievolkswirtschaft.ch/fr/2020/09/sheldon-10-2020fr/&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gautié, J. (2023).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benanav, A. (2019). The origins of informality: the ILO at the limit of the concept of unemployment. Journal of Global History, 14(1), 107-125.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The employment rate is also increasingly used as an alternative measure to the unemployment rate. In this article, however, we consider that it is not really an unemployment rate as its name suggests.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blanchard (2020), p. 46.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kalecki, M. (1943). Political aspects of full employment.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/fr/home/statistiques/travail-remuneration/salaires-revenus-cout-travail/indice-salaires.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/fr/home/statistiques/travail-remuneration/salaires-revenus-cout-travail/indice-salaires.html&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unemployment rate for all three metrics is consistently higher for women and foreigners, and in some cases for young people.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen, J. E., &amp;amp; King, J. D. (2004). Relative unemployment and gubernatorial popularity. The Journal of Politics, 66(4), 1267-1282; Ansolabehere, S., Meredith, M., &amp;amp; Snowberg, E. (2014). Mecro‐economic voting: Local information and micro‐perceptions of the macro‐economy. Economics &amp;amp; Politics, 26(3), 380-410.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wright, J. R. (2012). Unemployment and the democratic electoral advantage. American Political Science Review, 106(4), 685-702; Brännlund, A. (2021). Labor market conditions and partisan voting: How unemployment hurts the left. Political Behavior, 43(1), 363-396.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
